<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2629 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2629.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3552 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3552.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support.xml">

<!ENTITY RFC6418 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6418.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6419 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6419.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7556 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7556.xml">
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-sgros-dhcp-and-ipr-claim-analysis-00" ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <front>
    <title abbrev="DHCP_and_IPR">DHCP configuration in MIF and associated IPR claim</title>

    <author fullname="Stjepan Gros"
            initials="S." surname="Gros"
            role="editor">
      <organization>University of Zagreb</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Unska 3</street>
          <city>Zagreb</city>
          <code>10000</code>
          <country>HR</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>stjepan.gros@fer.hr</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Leonardo Jelenkovic"
            initials="L." surname="Jelenkovic"
            >
      <organization>University of Zagreb</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Unska 3</street>
          <city>Zagreb</city>
          <code>10000</code>
          <country>HR</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>leonardo.jelenkovic@fer.hr</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Dejan Skvorc"
            initials="D." surname="Skvorc"
            >
      <organization>University of Zagreb</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Unska 3</street>
          <city>Zagreb</city>
          <code>10000</code>
          <country>HR</country>
        </postal>
        <phone></phone>
        <email>dejan.skvorc@fer.hr</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="November" year="2015" day="23" />

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.
	 If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <keyword>mpvd</keyword>
    <keyword>dhcp</keyword>
    <keyword>ipr</keyword>
    <keyword>pvd</keyword>

    <abstract>
      <t>
The purpose of this draft is to analyze different options on
how DHCP can be used to configure PvD aware client. This is done
in light of IPR claim made by Huawei and the necessity to find
an option for implementation. In order for an option to be selected
it obviously must not interfere with the IPR made by Huawei, or,
the IPR has to be somehow invalidated. We also analyse IPR made by
Huawei in order to compare it to MIF proposal for DHCP configuration
and to assess how relevant this IPR claim is.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">

      <t>
      At IETF94 MIF Working Group decided to abandon drafts written so far
      and to wait for implementations that would serve as a basis for a
      new drafts <xref target="MIFminutes94" />. One of the problems was
      the IPR claim made by Huawei <xref target="HuaweiIPRClaim" />.
      </t>

      <t>
      This document has two purposes. The first is to identify the best path
      to follow for the implementation of client configuration using DHCP in
      a presence of multiple provisioning domains. The second is to present
      analysis of the IPR claim made by Huawei in order to see how it influences
      possible solutions. Since the licensing terms are too strict it is
      mandatory to avoid conflict with the given patent.
      </t>

      <t>
      This draft contains three core sections. In <xref target="requirements" />
      the requirements on the final solution are given. It is very important to
      agree on those in order to have criteria on which different solutions can
      be analyzed. Then, in <xref target="IPR_Claim" /> we do a thorough
      analysis of the IPR claim made by Huawei and also we analyse how it relates to
      the existing proposal. Finally, in <xref target="IPR_Claim" />
      we present different possibilities and analyze each one of them based on
      requirements defined and IPR claim made by Huawei.
      </t>

      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section anchor="requirements" title="Requirements">
      <t>
The solution to be defined and used has to fulfill the following requirements:
      </t>
<!--
      <t>List styles: 'empty', 'symbols', 'letters', 'numbers', 'hanging',
      'format'.</t>
-->

      <t><list style="symbols">

        <t>No IPR claims. The solution MUST be free of IPR claims, or if there
        are any IPR claims then they MUST be licensed in such a way to allow
        unrestricted implementations without any fees.</t>

        <t>Backwards compatibility. The solution MUST be be backwards compatible.
        This means that the old clients upon seeing messages defined by the
        DHCP solution must ignore it and correctly function without knowing
        for those messages.</t>

        <t>Efficiency of implementation. The solution SHOULD be as efficient as
        possible for the implementation. This means, for example, that messages
        defined by the final specification should be constructed in such a way
        to make an implementation as simple as possible.</t>

        <t>Efficiency of communication. The solution SHOULD be as efficient as
        possible for communication. This means, for example, that as few
        messages as possible should be necessary in order for the client to
        be fully configured.</t>

      </list></t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="IPR_Claim" title="Analysis of the IPR Claim made by Huawei">

      <t>
      Before continuing a big DISCLAIMER. No lawyer has participated in the
      development of the following text so you should take a note that this
      is only an engineering view of a potentialy very complex problem.
      </t>

      <t>
      The IPR claim made by Huawei <xref target="HuaweiIPRClaim" /> is based
      on US Patent #US20140344421 <xref target="US20140344421" />. The abstract
      of a given patent describes what is the patent about:
      </t>

      <t><list><t>
      A method for configuring a DHCPv6 client is provided. The method includes:
      a DHCPv6 client receiving a DHCPv6 advertisement message sent by a network
      device having a DHCPv6 function, the DHCPv6 advertisement message comprising
      a management domain identifier of the network device; if the DHCPv6 client
      does not save the management domain identifier, the DHCPv6 client sending
      a DHCPv6 request message to the network device; the DHCPv6 client receiving
      a DHCPv6 response message sent by the network device and completing
      configuration of the DHCPv6 client. A DHCPv6 client, a network device, and
      a network system are also provided. Through the technical solution, multiple
      network devices supporting a DHCPv6 server function can configure the same
      DHCPv6 client, so as to provide technical support for realizing IPv6 client
      and network multi-homing.</t>
      </list></t>

      <t>
      In the given paragraph, there are two key pieces of information:
      </t>

      <t><list style="numbers">
      <t>
      The term "management domain identifier".
      </t>

      <t>
      The last sentence which places the mechanism described by the patent into
      a context where it is used.
      </t>
      </list></t>

      <t>
      These two key parts are in direct correlation with the mechanism to configure
      MPvDs as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support" />.
      Namely, "management domain identifier" is basically PVD_ID and the last
      sentence describes multi-homing environment, which basically MPvD is also.
      Note that "multi-homing environment" can be achieved on a single network with
      multiple ISPs and multiple networks, each with its own ISP. The context of the
      patent is the former one, while of the MPvD is the latter one. To see that
      the MPvD context is a sinle ISP per each physical and/or virtual network
      one should take a look at Section 4 of MIF Architecture Document
      <xref target="RFC7556" />. In no case there is situation in which two or more
      sets of configuration parameters are received on a _single_ link, thus creating
      race condition situation, i.e. the first configuration set of parameters that
      reaches client, wins. This is very important distinction.
      </t>

      <t>
      In the following subsections we analyze separately two different parts of
      the patent, protocol part (Exibits 1 and 2) and the implementation part
      (Exibit 3). Protocol part is the
      more important, but implementation is also very important due to the
      patentability requirements <xref target="algorithmspatentable" />.
      </t>

      <section title="Detailed analysis of the protocol part">

        <t>
        Figure 1 in the patent claim describes scenario of client configuration
        via DHCPv6 from the client's perspective when patented configuration
        mechanism is used. Figure 3 shows the same, but from the server's
        perspective. According to the given description the following
        sequence of steps happens:
        </t>

        <t><list style="numbers">
        <t>
        Upon client sending SOLICIT message, DHCPv6 server sends ADVERTISE message.
        This message includes an option that defines "management domain identifier".
        Additional rules are mentioned later in the text concerning the SOLICIT
        message:

          <list style="numbers">
          <t>
          Paragraph [0045] says that client sends SOLICIT message but _without_
          an option "management domain identifier". Furthermore, judging by the
          [0045], DHCPv6 server MUST include "management domain identifier".
          </t>

          <t>
          In paragraph [0050] it says further that when client receives SOLICIT
          message with previously unknown "management domain identifier" then
          "the DHCPv6 client may send the DHCPv6 request message to the network
          device and store the management domain identifier of the network
          device. The DHCPv6 request message is adapted to request the network
          device to configure the DHCPv6 client."
          </t>

          <t>
          Then, paragraph [0046] contradicts paragraph [0045] by saying that "management
          domain identifier" doesn't have to be included. Yet, in that case the question
          is what makes so special this patent from regular DHCPv6 exchange.
          </t>

          <t>
          Also, in paragraph [0046] it says that the "management domain identifier"
          defines to WHICH MANAGEMENT DOMAIN NETWORK DEVICE BELONGS. According to this,
          "management domain identifier" identifies some management domain and not a
          set of configuration parameters that can belong to some management domain.
          This is emphasised by explicitly saying that "... management domain identifier
          may be a name of an ISP or a name of an organization."
          </t>

          </list>

        </t>

        <t>
        Client sends REQUEST message. There are few problems with the description in
        this part:

          <list>
          <t>
          There is ambiguity here as it doesn't specify
          weather client sends "management domain identifier" option in REQUEST or not.
          </t>

          <t>
          It sounds like there is unfinished sentence here. Namely, this part in
          the patent application says:

            <list style="empty"><t>
            [0043] 104: The DHCPv6 client sends a DHCPv6 request
            message to the network device and stores the management
            domain identifier, when the client does not store the management
            domain identifier.
            </t></list>

          Note the last part of the sentence, "when the client does not store the 
          management domain identifier". It doesn't make any sense! Reading through
          the later text (specifically paragraph [0050]) it seems to be a C/P error.
          Upon further thinking, it seems possible that it isn't an C/P error
          but it says that client stores "management domain identifier" when it
          doesn't have it already.
          </t>

          <t>
          The patent application doesn't define what happens when client sends
          REQUEST message to multicast address which is received by all other
          DHCP servers, i.e. what other DHCP servers not belonging to a given
          management domain do.
          </t>
  
          </list>

        </t>

        <t>
        As the final step DHCPv6 client receives configuration data in a
        REPLY message. This part is underwritten/underspecified. To see that
        here is quote from the relevant part of the patent:

          <list style="empty"><t>
          [0044] 106: The DHCPv6 client receives a DHCPv6 reply
          message from the network device and configures the
          DHCPv6 client according to the DHCPv6 reply message. The
          DHCPv6 reply message includes an IPv6 prefix assigned to
          the DHCPv6 client by the network device and a network
          configuration parameter assigned to the DHCPv6 client by
          the network device; or the DHCPv6 reply message includes
          an IPv6 address assigned to the DHCPv6 client by the net
          work device and a network configuration parameters assigned
          to the DHCPv6 client by the network device.
          </t></list>

        First, it says that IPv6 address or IPv6 prefix MUST be present
        in the configuration message. Also, if IPv6 prefix is present
        than a single network configuration parameter is assigned, while
        if it is IPv6 address then "a network configuration parameters"
        are present. In paragraph [0050] both are assumed to have a single
        parameter!
        </t>
        </list></t>

      </section>

      <section title="Detailed analysis of the implementation part">

        <t>
        Figures 4 and 5 in the patent claim show implementation of the
        given patent. The reason for this is that protocols (which are in
        essence distributed algorithms) can not be patented
        <xref target="algorithmspatentable" />. 
        </t>

        <t>
        Looking at the figures presented in the patent, there is no difference
        between the implementations that support "management domain identifier"
        and existing ones that don't support it. So, the question is what makes
        this proposed implementation in the patent so special? In other words,
        if no special implementation is necessary, then this implies that the
        patent isn't so special/new after all.
        </t>

      </section>
 
      <section title="Differences between the patent and draft-ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support">

        <t>
        There are differences between the patent and the solution as proposed
        in the draft:
        </t>

        <t><list style="numbers">

        <t>
        "Management domain" while isn't defined by the patent isn't used to identify
        set of a configuration parameters, but a whole domain managed by some
        authority. PvD, on the other hand, identifies a set of configuration parameters
        no matter to whom they belong.
        </t>

        <t>
        The context of the patent is a single network with multipe ISPs, while the
        context of MIF is multiple connections, each with a single ISP.
        </t>

        <t>
        Option with "management domain ID" is like any other option, i.e. it is not
        a container for the other options as in MPvD DHCP proposal.
        </t>

        <t>
        In the given patent there is 1 to 1 mapping between DHCP server and management
        domain. In MPvD, on the contrary, one DHCP server can host multiple provisioning
        domains.
        </t>

        <t>
        As per the patent only ADVERTISE message has "management domain identifier"
        option included.
        </t>

        <t>
        In the patent application management IDs are sent without being requested by the
        client. So, in case the client explicitly requests different management domain
        the patent doesn't apply.
        </t>

        <t>
        The mechanism in patent, as described, couldn't be implemented without first
        resolving some issues not defined precisely enough. (the case when client
        sends REQUEST on multicast address, possibly without "management domain
        identifier" - it is not clean how DHCP server belonging to other domains
        should react)
        </t>

        <t>
        The patent doesn't explicitly specify anything else being part of "management
        domain" other then IPv6 address or prefix.
        </t>

        <t>
        The patent specifies that IPv6 address or prefix must be in response.
        </t>

        </list></t>
      </section>

      <section anchor="ipr_conclusion" title="Conclusion">

        <t>
        The first conclusion is that this patent actually patents an algorithm,
        and since algorithms aren't patentable than the patent itself is invalid.
        </t>

        <t>
        The second conclusion is that introducing a configuration option with
        PVD_ID that functions as a container for other options isn't in collision with
        the given patent.
        </t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="OptionsForPvDProvisioning" title="Options for PvD provisioning">

      <t>
      The first step towards the selection of a possible solution is to
      enumeration all the options. 
      </t>

      <t>
      For a start, there MUST be a way for a network to convey information
      about specific PvD to a client. The most natural way of doing this is
      via DHCP and it can be done either implicitly or explicitly, and if
      explicitly furthermore it can be done directly or indirectly:

      <list style="symbols">

        <t>
        Implicit. The information that the parameters within a message belong
        to some particular PvD isn't contained within DHCP message itself but
        somewhere outside of it. This isn't an option since DHCP is used for
        network configuration and by placing related information somewhere else
        interleaves DHCP with something else. This in turn, complicates
        implementations and breaks layering rules.
        </t>

        <t>
        Explicit. The information that certain parameters within the message
        belong to some specific PvD is contained within the message itself.
        </t>

        <t>
        Direct. All the necessary information necessary to identify PvD are
        placed within the DHCP message.
        </t>

        <t>
        Indirect. Information about PvD isn't fully contained within DHCP
        message but has to be obtained by some other mean. 
        </t>

      </list>
      </t>

      <t>
      When information about PvD is explicit then it can be done in the
      following ways, first four of which are explicit while the last one
      is implicit:

      <list style="numbers">

      <t>
      A single option within DHCP message can define PvD the whole message
      belongs to. This approach has two problems. The first is backwards
      compatibility. Clients not aware of PvD will be confused with multiple
      configuration parameters. The second problem is that it resembles the
      IPR claim made by Huawei and analyzed in the previous section.
      </t>

      <t>
      Prefixing each option with an option that identifies PvD to which the
      given option belongs to. This approach has the problem of bloating
      DHCP message, and also there is a problem with backwards compatibility.
      </t>

      <t>
      Defining separate set of configuration options in which each contains
      PVD_ID and appropriate option. The problem with this approach is the
      number of options that should be duplicated.
      </t>

      <t>
      Using container option which holds all the options specific for a given
      PvD. This approach was used in the existing proposal of PvD configuration
      using DHCP messages <xref target="I-D.ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support" />.
      </t>

      <t>
      There is an indicator within DHCP message about availability of other
      PvDs. When PvD aware client receives such message, it requests
      additional configuration options, e.g. by using DHCP INFORM messages.
      DHCP INFORM messages could be used to obtain a list of all available
      PVD_IDs and to request specific PVD_IDs. This is an example of indirect
      configuration of a client.
      </t>

      </list>
      </t>

      <section anchor="dhcpcontainer" title="DHCP Container Option">

      <t>
      This approach is the same as the one proposed by <xref target="I-D.ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support" />.
      </t>

      </section>

      <section anchor="dhcpinform" title="Using DHCP INFORM">

      <t>
      In this approach during DHCP configuration client is only informed that
      there are different PvDs. The exchange of messages is:

      <list style="numbers">

        <t>
        Client sends DHCP SOLICIT message with an option that specifys
        client's support of PvD.
        </t>

        <t>
        Server sends DHCP ADVERTISE message with an option that specifys
        servers's support of PvD.
        </t>

        <t>
        Client notes all the servers that support PvDs and sends DHCP REQUEST
        message to multicast address telling all DHCP servers which DHCP
        server for basic configuration parameters was selected.
        </t>

        <t>
        Server send DHCP REPLY and confirms client's parameters.
        </t>

        <t>
        Client issues DHCP INFORM REQUEST to each DHCP server that indicated
        support for PvDs. This request includes no specific PvD.
        </t>

        <t>
        Based on client's request. each server responds with a list of available
        PvDs. Each element consits of PVD_ID and, if available, a link (like a
        Proxy configuration mechanism that contains URL) that points to the
        description of PvD (QoS, reachability).
        </t>

        <t>
        Client selects PvDs and for each PvD sends DHCP INFORM REQUEST this time
        with a specific PVD ID.
        </t>

        <t>
        Server responds with a configuration parameters for requested PVD ID.
        </t>

      </list>
      </t>

      </section>

    </section>

    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
      </t>
    </section>

    <!-- Possibly a 'Contributors' section ... -->

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo includes no request to IANA.</t>

      <t>All drafts are required to have an IANA considerations section (see
      <xref target="I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis">the update of
      RFC 2434</xref> for a guide). If the draft does not require IANA to do
      anything, the section contains an explicit statement that this is the
      case (as above). If there are no requirements for IANA, the section will
      be removed during conversion into an RFC by the RFC Editor.</t>
    </section>

    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>All drafts are required to have a security considerations section.
      See <xref target="RFC3552">RFC 3552</xref> for a guide.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
     1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629; here (as shown)
     2. simply use a PI "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds: include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

     Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
     If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included files in the same
     directory as the including file. You can also define the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
     with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be either in the local
     filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

    <references title="Normative References">
      <!--?rfc include="http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml"?-->

      &RFC2119;

      &RFC6418;

      &RFC6419;

      &RFC7556;

    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">
      <!-- Here we use entities that we defined at the beginning. -->

      &RFC2629;

      &RFC3552;

      &I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis;

      &I-D.ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support;

      <!-- A reference written by an organization not a person. -->

      <reference anchor="HuaweiIPRClaim"
                 target="https://datatracker.ietf.org/ipr/2648/">
        <front>
          <title>Huawei Technologies Co.,Ltd's Statement about IPR related to draft-ietf-mif-mpvd-dhcp-support</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Huawei Technologies Co.</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2014" month="August" day="1" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="US20140344421"
                 target="http://www.google.com/patents/US20140344421">
        <front>
          <title>Method for configuring dhcpv6 client, dhcpv6 client, network device, and network system</title>

          <author>
            <organization>Huawei Technologies Co.</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2015" month="August" day="3" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="MIFminutes94"
                 target="https://www.ietf.org/proceedings/94/minutes/minutes-94-mif">
        <front>
          <title>IETF 94th MIF minutes</title>

          <author>
            <organization>IETF94</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2015" month="November" day="22" />
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="algorithmspatentable"
                 target="http://programmers.stackexchange.com/questions/32482/can-an-algorithm-be-patented">
        <front>
          <title>Can an algorithm be patented?</title>

          <author>
            <organization>StackExchange</organization>
          </author>

          <date year="2010" month="December" day="30" />
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
